[Music]
hello everybody
great to see you all welcome to the
28th live episode of ask kabajit
so let me take a look at who's out there
we have
omkar sanika abhinav
hello everybody nice to see you all it's
great to see your smiling faces
so as you know today we discuss
education
and i had initially planned to actually
give a kind of a monologue
and gave a presentation about the
education system its
problems and the solutions that i would
like to give
but you guys have asked so many
questions i mean
i'm blown away within with the number of
questions you've asked
so that's why i have decided that i will
answer your questions today i will take
up a whole bunch of questions from you
today
that you have asked in the comments so
today will be basically a warm
up episode and next week i'm gonna do a
proper presentation about the education
system
its history its problems and the
solutions that we need to implement
okay so that so today is a warm-up
episode but i'm gonna answer all your
questions today
as many as i can so with that said
let's get right into it with your
questions
so ashutosh asks what's the purpose of
education according to you
and how does your ideal education system
look like
so the purpose of education see the
education system
its purpose is to serve the country and
to serve
the students that's that's the purpose
of the education system
and so what that means is that the
education system is supposed to give the
country
the best possible people right
it should uh empower the students
it should build up their confidence
build up their skills
it should build up their ability to be
successful
and productive and valuable adults who
will contribute
the best of their ability to the to the
country so it the education system's
basic uh purpose is to ensure that it
allows the students to discover who they
are what are their aptitudes and
abilities
and it should basically help them
fulfill their true
and complete potential it means that
once you are done with the education
system you should be
confident that you can deal with the
world
that is the purpose of the education
system and its purpose is to
empower the country and ensure that the
future generations
are capable of taking the country
forward in the correct
direction its purpose is to produce
people with all kinds of talents people
who are good at science people who are
good at sport people who are good at
art people are good who are good at
technology people who are good at
teaching
and people who are leaders and people
who are good at entrepreneurship
and business so its purpose is to
maximize your potential that is the
purpose of the education system
and that is what an ideal education
system looks like
now it's clear that the indian education
doesn't do any of these things
it does the opposite so that is why this
is such an important
topic so it's a good question it's a
great question to start off with
all right is education leading to
success a dumb idea
because only a small minority is going
to be successful
what should be the objective of
education and what outcomes and
character should we expect from the
education system
so only a small minority is going to be
successful
i mean how does one define success
everybody has a different definition of
success what is success
is becoming becoming a millionaire
success is becoming a billionaire
success
is becoming you're the the chief
minister of prime minister success
or is basically achieving your full
potential in life
isn't that success not everybody needs
to become a millionaire or a billionaire
or a prime minister or president or
whatever everybody doesn't have that
ambition
the success how do you define success
success is that you
live a happy and fulfilling and
productive life
that is the true meaning of success
everybody is different
no two individuals are the same
everyone's definition of success
needs to be different and that's why we
have to discover
who we truly are and what our aptitudes
are
and then we can define our own success
today we define success by the
what the kind of marks we get in our
exams and the kind of job we get
and there are only a certain kind of
certain kinds of jobs available and
that's why we have very narrow
definitions of success
this needs to change everybody is
different
everybody should be empowered to achieve
their full potential in
the direction that is best for them and
that is success
so i think every single individual every
single man woman
girl boy can be successful in their own
way
and they can be happy i mean if you live
a happy and fulfilling
fulfilling life then that is the best
success you can ask for
so that is the thing that is what
education needs to do
it needs you it needs to equip
students with the tools
needed to achieve success that what they
define
as success on their own terms it does
success doesn't mean that you have to
defeat somebody success doesn't mean
that others have to fail
right everybody can succeed together and
that is the mark
that is the signature of a prosperous
country and society so that's what needs
to happen
and that is the uh
purpose of the education system what
outcomes in character should we expect
in the education system it should tell
you what is right and what is wrong it
should it should give you the
it should equip you with all the tools
you need
to become a confident human being
a confident adult who knows that they
have the tools
and abilities needed to succeed in the
world they should be ready to take on
the world once they are out of the
education system
that is the outcome and character that
we need they should know what is right
what is wrong
they should tell be able to tell good
from bad they should be able to
understand what is the national interest
they should be able to understand and
value
their ancient culture so these are the
outcomes in character
we seek from the education system and
once again
india's education system does the
opposite and that is why this is such
an important topic
asks what should be the motivation
behind
studying or learning something and how
should a student learn
excellent question the motivation behind
studying or learning something is
see the basic motivation is curiosity
you should know
what fascinates you you know when when
when you have a small kid like two
or three years old before they go to
school they are so curious
they are so imaginative they are
fascinated with everything they ask a
thousand questions
why is the sky blue why do butterflies
fly why are flowers the way they are why
are they colored
in a certain manner why do ducks look
different from crows
so many questions and this is the
curiosity that is the motivation behind
studying and learning things
now as you grow older you start to
understand who you are
and and what kind of interests you have
and
that is essentially what you need to
pursue in life in order in order to live
a happy and successful and
fulfilling life so the motivation behind
studying on learning anything is to ask
yourself what
fascinates you what interests you and
how can you get
better at that it has to be it has to be
driven from inside you
need to have the drive from inside
today's education system it basically
imposes a certain curriculum upon you
and nobody has basically any interest in
that it is something that's forced upon
you
it's something that's shoved down your
throat for for the first
20 years of your life and that's why
there's no motivation
the motivation is learning should be
self-driven self-directed
that is what we need to have and how
should a student learn
excellent question you learn
we learn by asking questions that's the
first thing curiosity you need to be
curious ask questions
ask questions of your teachers ask
questions of yourself
ask questions to the internet ask
questions to whatever books you have
ask questions and secondly skepticism
don't believe what your teachers tell
you don't believe what i tell you don't
believe what your textbooks tell you
be skeptical find as many sources
of information as you can to answer the
same question and then use
and then trust your intelligence to tell
you which which of these sources
is telling you the truth once you start
trusting your judgment
and developing the judgment by looking
at lots of different sources
that's when you start learning and
that's when you build the power of
discrimination of right and wrong
of the correct answer and the wrong
answer so it's a lifelong process you
don't
learn for only 15 20 years and then
you're done with it
it's a lifelong process so that is how
you learn you learn by asking questions
and secondly by being skeptical and
thirdly by understanding the scientific
method
now i cannot teach you the scientific
method right now maybe i can do a
separate
thing for that because that's not the
topic but learn the scientific method
science is essential everybody needs to
understand science i'm not saying you
should learn quantum physics or rocket
science or
algebra trigonometry calculus all that i
am saying you should understand the very
fundamental of science
which is the scientific method it's
something even a child can understand
so you everybody needs to understand
that the scientific
methodology is the key to success in
life
right you can be an artist and all but
while learning you need to employ
the scientific method so these are the
keys to success
and the keys to learning the right way
tanvi asks do you think that education
should be free for all
if yes then how if no then why not
can the internet completely destroy the
traditional education system in the long
run
i'm assuming convey that you but by
traditional education system you mean
the
the current indian colonial education
system right so i'm assuming that's what
you mean
so to answer your first question do i
think education should be free for all
uh yes absolutely i have said this in
the past on this channel
i firmly believe that knowledge should
be free
knowledge should be free knowledge
should be available to everyone
without imposing a course cost on the
knowledge
right education should be free for all
if yes then how well the government
it is their job to provide education
look if you look at the history of india
you will realize that there were certain
things that were always free in india
education was always free indian in
india
always before the colonial period which
is the past 1000 years
education was always free it was open to
everybody girls boys
whatever stratum of society or from did
not matter it was always open to
everybody
it was always free and how was this
possible the
state subsidized education whatever
part of india you were living in you
would have different kings queens
whatever
it was their duty to fund every temple
every vihara every university
and everything was provided for free the
entire upkeep in maintenance of the of
the university
the upkeep and maintenance and living
expenses everything of the staff
and of the students you did not have to
take a big education loan
and pay monthly fees or yearly fees and
then you
you have to find accommodation and pay a
monthly rent none of that was there
everything was taken care of so that's
the first thing education was always
taken care of by the state it was free
to everybody and if you were
good enough to go to a higher level even
that was free at the highest level also
education was free
and not just to indians even to people
from other countries
schwann zhang the chinese monk who came
to india has
very clearly recorded all this so
education
has traditionally been free in india
secondly health care has always been
free in india
even during the princely states time
during british occupation of india
healthcare used to be free even right
after so-called independence in 4748
until the princely states were abolished
and destroyed
healthcare was still free so education
should be free
healthcare should be free and social
services should be free these are the
three characteristics of a civilized
society
what this tells you is that india is not
a civilized society today and neither is
the west which is commercialized
education
india is blindly following the western
capitalistic model
in which everything has a price
education is
something that only those who can afford
it can get health care
well if you are rich you will get health
care if you are poor
too bad rest in peace you know
so this is the kind of stupid regressive
backward system that india has adopted
from the west and that is a
crying shame it needs to change so yes
education should be free
will the internet destroy this uh the
current 21st century education system i
think it is already undermining all this
uh
the value of the degrees and the value
of the universities and colleges
everything is online now it's a great
thing
and it needs to be taken to this logical
conclusion so yes it
it is definitely already
undermining this very poor education
system that we have it's it's basically
digging the grave
for the system and i hope that things
will change
soon
abhishek asks how can the education
be equal for poor and rich students when
the needs and requirements are different
see abhishek i disagree with this
assumption that the needs and
requirements of
poor and rich students are different the
requirements and needs are all the same
they all need the same education
they all need the same tools needed to
succeed in life
that's all every student needs whether
they're rich or poor boy or girl
whatever religion they are whatever
language
people speak whatever so-called caste
they are from
whatever it is everybody has the same
requirements
a good and in a good education system a
good education
an education that empowers them to
succeed in life and to achieve their
full potential
so it is what that is what's needed and
today that's not the case right
obviously we have all these
problems in our education system so what
how can it be made
equal well by reforming the education
system it's simple
make education compulsory and free and
make it convenient
make it online there are lots of reforms
that can be done today because of
technology
you know technology can empower the
people of india if the government of
india so chooses
so it's simple make it free make it a
universal right
make it the government's duty to provide
high quality top class free education
system
in a way that is convenient to everyone
all right so how do you think the
government should fund the education
system
because if we want to provide first
class education to every kid in our
country
it will cost hundreds of billions of
dollars per year
or should we make a merit system and
provide the best education to the most
brilliant kids in our
country very good question
you are absolutely right education
providing
first-class education to every kid in
the country
will cost hundreds of billions of
dollars per year
um yeah it will it will call
it will definitely cost billions of
dollars per year maybe tens of billions
i don't think it will cross several
hundreds of billions of dollars
i don't think so it's possible to scale
it
using technology and make it cost
effective
so how should the government fund the
education system right
you know the chinese
uh they reformed their education system
starting from the late 20th century
the past three decades they have been
reforming their education system step by
step by step by step iterative
reforms of the system and they have
invested
not hundreds of billions of dollars into
it they have invested
trillions of dollars into reforming and
revamping
and overhauling completely their
education system
they have invested trillions of dollars
into this and they started doing this
when the gdp was less than what india's
gdp is today
so they have always had this ambition
and this clear vision of where they want
to be
so they started making these enormous
investments in the system
education system when they were a third
world country when they were poorer than
india
when their overall gdp was smaller than
what our gdp is today
so if they could do it if they had the
gumption
and the will and the vision to do it
even when they were poor
then why is india not doing something
similar today it is definitely possible
does it does does the indian government
have the money for it
hell yes it has all the money in the
world
it all depends on where they invest the
money today
the money is being invested in populist
schemes that will get you votes
things need to change we need a clear
vision we need the right leadership
in order to take the country forward
everything is possible we have the money
the country has the money
i mean what are we paying taxes for
okay people will say that very few
people pay income tax in the country
okay i agree
what about everything else every time
you make a purchase of anything
there is a tax on it there is what i
mean there is
gst and whatnot first of all
you pay income tax so you the salary you
get is already taxed
on top of that anytime you buy anything
at all you are being taxed again
we are getting patrol oil from the
middle east at a certain rate
it is being sold to the citizens at
least twice or twice the rate
so the government is taxing everything
it has
enormous revenues so
why is this revenue not being utilized
correctly that's my question
it can be done the government does have
the funds to do this
kostov asks does the indian government
have
enough financial risk abilities
to run free good and competitive
education for students till the
graduation
yes like i said the indian government
does have it it has enormous
streams of revenue in enormous sources
of revenue income
tax is the least of these even if we
abolish income tax
if the government will still earn
enormous amounts of money from taxation
itself
there is taxes on everything every
service every good
everything is taxed right i mean petrol
like i said petrol is is
priced at like two or three times the
actual cost any service that you get if
you
if you buy a house you have to pay a tax
on that if you buy a car or
vehicle you have to pay tax on that if
you uh go to a restaurant and
and have a have a meal there you're
gonna pay tax on that
you buy vegetables you're gonna pay tax
on that
and every municipality levies an
additional tax
on every small business which is off the
books fyi
it's a weekly tax that is not used for
the country it's used for the
for for i'm not saying every
municipality would be doing this
but i would think many would be doing
that yeah i'm not naming names but yeah
so there are all these taxes that are
imposed on the people but though that
money is not used
for the country it is time that this
money is used for the service of the
country
and its people because the highest
morale vishnugov
said the highest morality for the king
is that his kingdom and his people
should prosper that's the only duty a
king has
and that applies to every other leader
that we have today in our
colonial governance system so yes india
does have enough financial
abilities to run excellent world-class
free
and competitive education system for the
students until
until they finish their education
clearly it does
kavita asks how do we end tuition
culture
according to a report a huge number of
parents have taken loans in order to pay
coaching class fees
for competitions like g e n e eet and
upsc
this is the bane of india this coaching
class
culture this tuition culture i mean it's
all because of this competitive
competitive exams that are like there
once a year if you fail then your entire
year is wasted you know
and it's also because there is such a
scarcity of high quality education
there are only a few few iits and a few
other big institutions
and the entirety of the country's
student population
is desperate to get into those and
therefore it is the
the interest systems exams are so
competitive and that's what these
coaching classes they they
exploit this problem and the government
actually
is very happy with the system you know
it is uh
empowering the coaching classes in this
entire system so it is basically a
parasitical system
that is leeching of the country it is
providing no real value
so how do we end this we need reforms in
education we did very
significant reforms in education system
i mean these exams first of all
why can't we have enough iits why can't
we have at least one iit
in every state minimum i would say there
should be one iit in every district
why can't we do this every student who
is
who is capable of rising to that level
of education
should get that education why should it
why should there be a scarcity
of of of seats in these institutions
every single student who is capable
of studying at the level should be
allowed to study at that level
right that's that would do away with
this need for this
horrific hyper competitive exams
so this is all because of the scarcity
culture that has there is a
a leftover from the nehruvian regime era
and we are still continuing that
socialistic practice of
of creating artificial scarcities for
everything if india were to invest
like you said like someone said hundreds
of billions of dollars into the
education system
then this artificial scarcity will end
right so these are the reforms that we
need in this country
we need massive investments into
education
akash asks do you think coding is a
crucial skill
and should be taught to every student
from earlier classes i think coding is
an extremely important skill the future
is
all high tech the future is all online
technology is the future
so coding is definitely going to be one
of the core skill sets that will allow
you to
basically uh excel
in life if you know coding then you will
and if you keep on learning new
new coding languages and uh software
packages etc then it's going to really
make things very easy for you you will
basically have employ
not employment but you will have always
you will always have a stream of income
so coding is definitely as a crucial
skill and it's and it's easy it's just
logic you know everyone most students in
india are afraid of mathematics
and the reason for that is that they're
not taught mathematics properly in
in their kindergarten and primary school
level
and once your foundations are bad you
can never learn higher skills
and that's why everyone is scared of
mathematics actually mathematics is the
easiest skill to acquire
if you're taught properly it's the
easiest thing in the world mathematics
but it has to be taught properly from
the very beginning and the same goes for
coding coding is just
logic everybody can learn coding
most people can learn coding and
basically you can become a full stack
developer
starting from absolutely zero within 12
months
that's how easy it is to learn coding
and everything all the information is
available online for free
you can get full entire courses high
quality
courses in any programming language
online on youtube
in other places for free and you don't
need to buy expensive
hardware to do coding or software to do
coding
most of the tools you need are all free
available online
all you need is a computer a laptop
that's it
so i think coding is something all
youngsters should learn
i think everybody can learn it it's not
difficult at all
and it is something that will really
empower you and ensure
that you are never you are never held
hostage by the degree system and the
in the in the employment system and all
you can live your entire life as a
freelancer if you're a good coder
if you have a good portfolio which is
not hard to create so yes i think
everybody should learn it in their free
time
uh and yeah the education system should
also
uh focus on coding if one were to change
the system it's something that
will definitely come in very handy for
everybody and for the country as well
aj asks what's my take on cl on coding
platforms which are taking huge money
from parents of five-year-olds for the
education that's already freely
available
it's a scam it's a scam and people need
to understand that you don't need to pay
any money to learn coding everything is
available online for free
you just know you just need to know
where to look
just go to youtube and check out
whatever if you're learning
i mean one of the most popular languages
today is python to start off with
beginners language
you will find lots of python courses on
youtube
lots and lots of them you know entire
playlists you can
start from scratch and become a proper
proficient
coder and the same goes for html css
javascript
whatnot so i think it is it is it is
terrible that these coding platforms are
taking advantage of the fact that elder
that older people don't understand
technology
and they are afraid of it so they they
want to invest
money into all this you know you can
learn everything for free so
this is a scam and i'm i'm disappointed
that it is probably for rating today
nishant asks i think we are ruining our
regional and national languages by using
english words and phrases in our
day-to-day conversation
we are shrinking our languages
vocabulary will studying in our mother
tongue solve the problem
and can it be implemented nationwide
and learning english only as a language
yes studies have shown
worldwide that students the
children learn any concept
best in their mother tongue
and therefore this requirement to first
learn a foreign language and then
learn various concepts in education it
is
a concept that is way past its its its
date
you know and this demonstrates that we
are
so mentally colonized our leadership is
so mentally colonized our entire system
is so colonized even today i mean the
british left 70 years ago but we are
still using
everything that the british gave us i
mean which they
imposed upon us their language their
colonial judicial system their colonial
bureaucracy
their colonial ips their colonial uh
parliamentary system
everything and our so-called leaders
are so invested in the system that
brought them to power
that they don't want to change anything
and therefore india needs some leaders
who are
willing to destroy
the system that brought them to power
and remake it in a way that it serves
the country
and so yes i am very much
very strongly in favor of of eliminating
english completely
and having a two language system instead
of of the three language or five
language system that we have today
mother tongue and a civilizational
language that's it no english we don't
need english
do the chinese study english
those chinese who go to the us they do
learn english but
china is progressing so rapidly without
the use of english
there is this misconception among india
indian people
that english is the language of science
and technology what absolute nonsense
do the japanese develop their entire
all the technology in in english japan
is the
most technologically advanced nation in
the world everything is done in japanese
their entire education system is in
japanese their
english is very poor and they are
perfectly happy with it
and the same goes for the for the
chinese everything is in chinese
so why are we so obsessed with english
it is hampering
this country it is hampering the
progress of every child
it is it is pulling the country backward
we need to do away with english in our
education system
the reason why english is uh so
important is because every job interview
is conducted in english
if you don't know english then you're
looked upon as a is an inferior person
etc
so it has to start with the education
system and then and the government needs
to give clear guidelines to every
corporation and everybody that you need
to do with english
it has to come from the top so yes it
will really help the country if
all the education is done in the mother
tongue and in a civilizational language
only two languages
no english no foreign language
aj asks why is higher education only
given in the english language well that
continues with the previous question
because india's system is a coronary
system the british never really left
see basically
uh india was given
independence it was independence was
given to india
we did not take independence from the
british
the way to take independence from a
foreign occupier
is by destroying that person is by
defeating them
in warfare or in battle it is all about
violently overthrowing the foreign
occupying
regime when you do that you gain
independence on your own terms
and therefore the leadership that
emerges out of that independence is a
leadership that strongly opposes
every foreign thing that was imposed on
your country and that's when you start
straight away with decolonization now
when
the foreign occupier hands over
independence to you
as a gift then they do it on their terms
and they will hand over power to people
they prefer
and that's what happened in india so the
power was handed over to
we know who right we know what happened
and therefore we got independence on the
terms that the british set
and that's why everything is still
continuing as if the british never left
and that is why higher education is
still only given in the english language
and that's why all our politicians are
invested in the system
that the british gave us so that that is
the reason we are still colonized we
have never decolonized
the moment a foreign invader leaves the
first
thing you have to do is to undo
everything they have done
because whatever they did whatever they
imposed upon you was worth their own
benefit not for your benefit
so that is the first thing that needs
that should have been done after the
british left
that was to undo everything that was to
remove every british system and
institution and start from scratch with
an indian system
so even now we have not done that and
that is why we are still
conversing in english and learning in
english
namrata asks what should be the place of
english as a subject
in the indian education system school
level and higher
we need to eliminate english entirely
that is the place of english it has no
business being in the indian education
system
it is an inferior language
which is ironic considered considering
the fact that i'm talking to you in
english
but that is the state of the country
today we are all mentally colonized
myself included unfortunately aditya
asks
should sanskrit be made the official
language of india
and how can this task be carried out
when there are so many people
in our country and government who will
oppose this initiative
should sanskrit be made the official
language of india 100
yes that is the only language that has
the stature
of being the civilization language of
india for thousands of years
it is the language that we exported
throughout asia even today
in indonesia and other places people
have sanskrit names and we
ourselves are basically renouncing our
civilizational heritage
the only language that
has the status that can regain the
status of a civilization language of a
national language
is sanskrit i know many people will not
like it they will say this is sanskrit
imposition this is
what aryan imposition north indian
portion imposition
what utter nonsense
the chola dynasty the chula empire the
great
magnificent glorious chola empire spread
sanskrit and hinduism hinduism
throughout southeast asia all the way up
to the philippines
right they were tamil speaking people
they spread sanskrit
and please don't tell me that people in
malaysia etc speak tamil that's because
the
cholas spread tamil there no
the people in malaysia and other
countries who speak tamil are a
consequence
are there because of british colonial
practices they send lots of indians
there
to work for them etc that's why there
are tamil speaking people
in singapore malaysia etc it's not
because of the cholas fyi
the cholas spread sanskrit and hinduism
throughout southeast asia because it is
india's civilizational language
there is no tamil what's a sanskrit war
it is only something that has been
created after independence by these
southern indian politicians for their
own personal gain
okay so the only language that deserves
to be the national language official
language
in india is sanskrit and we can revive
it
of course there will be so many people
in the country and the government who
will oppose this initiative
and that's why india needs a leader who
can impose this
who can impose his will or her will on
the nation
and do what is right for the country
despite the opposition that is called
leadership
we don't have that leadership today
there is no such thing as
leadership by consensus there is no such
thing as
reforms by consensus we will do the
reform when everyone is on board
i will take a decision as a leader only
when everyone agrees what nonsense
leadership is about facing opposition
staring the opposition down
and doing what is best for your people
regardless of any opposition that is
called leadership
do we have that today ask yourselves so
it has to be done
regardless of any any opposition people
will oppose
every leader faces a position every
great leader
has faced a great deal of opposition but
they have still succeeded in doing the
right thing
we need leadership of that stature today
okay this is the next question yes it's
a fact that the indian education system
is outdated
but how do we convince our parents that
going through this outdated system
doesn't guarantee a successful career
and there are so many other ways to
acquire skills that could
make you earn money how do we change our
parents
mindset that's a good question
you know after people reach a certain
age they become
set in their thinking in their ways and
they
basically refuse to to
learn anything new and to entertain
different
ideas from what they have been brought
up believing and i think this age is
around the age of 40 after that people
become very
very rigid and that's just human nature
okay that's not a character defect
it's just human nature
and so how can you convince your parents
you basically can't convince your
parents
it's it's very hard to to change
people's opinions
and well they obviously want what is
best
for you in their in their opinion and
they think what's best for you
in their opinion in their experience is
going through this
horrific education system and getting a
nice stable
low paying sarcari job government job or
some private job
and having a long steady slow career
until you yourself get old
i mean that's what generations of
indians have been brought up
because that was the only safety net
they had
because in the 60s 70s 80s 90s even the
2000s
there were very few private jobs the
only way to have a secure stable life
was a government job
and the only way to go to government job
was to go
through the grind of the system
education system and get a paper degree
in your hand
and then apply please sir please give me
a job that was the only way to have a
stable life so i understand their
mindset it's not their fault
they want what's best for you so you
may not be able to convince them what i
would say is that i mean
obviously your parents are the ones who
are funding your education
so you're gonna have to go along with
that i would say that you need to
invest some time in yourself in addition
to whatever you're learning in the
system
and spend some extra time learning some
skills
online for free so acquire some skills
do some extra work hustle like people
would say
learn extra skills and then use that in
in your in the
in the future in your career that's the
only solution you have
if you're a student who is dependent
on his or her parents for education
because until you start earning you are
clearly dependent on your parents
and well they have certain beliefs and
you can't change those
okay ombowser asks why why do our
parents think that only the english
medium schools are best
but when you say when you think about it
this english medium schools are only
spreading their culture
over the world what are my thoughts see
our parents
everyone's parents well they have
grown up in the system and today it is
still true that if you don't speak
english well
then you will not get a good job
unfortunately
the first thing they look at they look
into is how well do you speak english
what sort of accent do you speak in
how fluent is your english
how well do you speak it how good is
your vocabulary are you confident
if you if you are good at english then
it becomes like
uh 10 times easier to then pass the to
then go through the rest of the job
interview process
so unfortunately in the system that we
are in today in this country
english is is a prerequisite for any
kind of success
and that's why your parents are right to
think today as of today
that english medium students schools are
the only way for
students to succeed in life until this
system is changed
this is going to continue unfortunately
so that's why
it is up to the government to change
this into and to
end this monopoly of english or the
education system and the job market
so your parents are right in thinking
that because if you don't speak english
if you don't learn
english properly then you are going to
have a lot of trouble getting a good job
or a high paying job
unfortunately that is a situation that
we are in today
and you are right these english medium
schools they spread foreign culture
in foreign values and and foreign
morality and all that
and which is basically antithetical to
indian
culture and indian morality so that is
the unfortunate
situation we are in today so that's why
we need education reforms
richie says i'm a class 12 student
and i'm honestly just way too confused i
have no clue about what to do
what would you say to confused students
like me who are just
unhappy with the education system and
have no clue about what they want to do
look richie when you're in class 12 it
is natural for you to be confused
it's too early for you to know anything
it's too early to figure out how the
world works you don't know what's there
in the future
you don't know what the educate what the
job system is like what the future is
going to be like it's natural to be
confused
so don't feel bad that you're confused
i'll tell you what you need to do
you need to educate yourself beyond the
education system you need to go through
the 1200 or whatever exam in college or
whatever it is
in order to be a good candidate for the
job market
but it's quite possible that in the
wi-fi next five to ten years the job
market will change
entirely completely it's very possible
so what you need to do
is learn certain skills skills is the
most important thing
first of all if you are good at uh
i think every student is good at this
learn coding like i said to akash
learn coding learn various skills like
that
uh understand how the internet works
learn coding learn things like if you
are if you have if you have the aptitude
for this
uh graphic design etc which you can
learn online
and skills like that skills that are
that are going to be useful in the long
run
and also understand finance understand
the economy economics
understand personal finance learn about
entrepreneurship
learn about stock market all that these
things i mean the one
crucial thing the education system
doesn't teach us is finance personal
finance
so once you're out of the education
system you're clueless
as to how to earn money how to save
money what to do with your money how to
invest money all those things
so learn these things and learn some
real life skills
such as coding start with python or
something learn coding learn web
development these things you can learn
for free you can learn online
so and these tools will basically ensure
that you are future proof
no matter what happens you will have
skills that you would be able to
leverage
and it will ensure that you have a good
income so learn these skills learn all
these skills that future proof you and
learn about personal finance
that is essential that's critical to
long-term success in life
learning what money is and how to use
money
so do that and and things will turn out
fine
one more says india has a great amount
of engineers i.t experts and scientists
then what's stopping the progress the
trillion dollar question
india has so many engineers and
i.t people and scientists and degree
holders
masters degree holders phd holders
and why is india not progressing the
answer my friends is that these degrees
are worthless they don't impart any real
skills
you have a master's degree a must you're
a master in whatever subject you are
and yet you don't know how to you don't
know anything about the subject
the only skill you acquire in the indian
education system
is to is how to pass exams and how to
get good marks and exams
that is the only skill you acquire in
the indian education system
how to get good marks and how to clear
exams
and how to navigate the horrors of the
indian education system
you don't really learn any skills let's
say you are
you're you're learning computer science
you're doing a master's degree in
computer science
you know what what you need to do in
order to pass the exam
you need to write an essay you need to
write essays there will be a three hour
question paper
in your first year and again in your
second year in which you will be
required to
write long essays about what is computer
science
and there'll be some stupid projects
that you have to do in which you can
basically copy paste some code and all
that and it will be it'll be fine
so these are the standards that our
education system has it's
these are just rituals that you have to
perform if you learn how to perform this
ritual then you will get your degree
but you will not get any real knowledge
of the subject
and you will not acquire any real skills
so when somebody comes out of the
education system with a master's degree
in computer science
and they get an id job they're clueless
as to what to do
because they have no actual skills and
they have to be taught these skills from
zero
that is the situation we are in that is
the kind of education system we have
and that is why despite these millions
of engineers and degree holders and
so-called scientists
india is not progressing at all because
our education system
doesn't give you the tools needed to
succeed
in whatever discipline you have chosen
and secondly
because the education system is all
about rote memorization like i said
and it is it is it completely neglects
research and development your professors
in whatever
institution you are whatever institute
you are in
what research do they do do they do any
original research
some of them in iits and some big
universities will publish some
so called research papers every year
which are just rehashes of
old research there is no actual research
being done
in india there is no scientific r d at
all in the academic system
and these are the reasons why there is
zero progress in india
despite having millions of degree
holders engineers i.t experts scientists
and whatnot
that's the reason
aj asks parallel coaching industry in
india grew as there was a gap
that our education system could not fill
do you think now the people controlling
this massive industry will let any
education systems
take place well this system
this coaching uh industry it is
making millionaires the people who run
these coaching classes
in this coaching institutions they are
making enormous
insane amounts of money out of the
system
so so basically they are deeply invested
in
ensuring that this system continues and
they clearly have political clout many
politicians have ties with them etc
and that is the reason why there is no
progress that is the reason why more and
more coaching classes are coming up
there is a reason why there are so many
so-called private universities and
private colleges and beamed universities
etc coming up
it is just an industry it's a money
making machine
that churns out these degrees that are
worthless
so that's the thing they will not they
do not want any education reforms to
take place they are very happy with the
system that we have
and that is why i keep saying india
needs leaders
who are willing to take the bull by the
horns
and despite whatever opposition is there
do the right thing and reform the system
clean up the garbage
the filth out of the system and
basically create a new system from
scratch
that basically empowers the people and
takes the country forward in the right
direction
akash asks when the degree when the
value of degrees
has has reduced appreciably in the near
future
will the value of iits and other
institutes of national importance
also plummet absolutely
the iit is basically they have lost
whatever stature they once had
uh i think it was in the early 2000s
that that reservation system was
implemented
in the iits not just in the students who
could enter the iit but also in the in
the
staff so the entire
the quality was was diluted very badly
so there was a time in the early 2000s
in the 90s etc when the
indian institute of technology were
among the top 10 educational institutes
in the world in the
in the in the stem field science and
technology etc
today you will not find them even in the
top 100 in the world that's how
badly they have fallen the iits and
also other institutes of national
importance so all they do is they turn
out degrees and their degrees of a
certain value based upon what
institution it is if it's an iit it has
a certain value
if it is something else it has a certain
value but now
like you say the value of degrees is
plummeting
because now now that you actually have
some private players in the country some
private industries
they want skills skills is what matters
if you have a new comment come into a
company with a degree
you're going to have to train them from
zero on the other hand if you have
somebody who is coming with
certain skills then you won't have to
train them from zero and they'll be
valuable
and productive from day one itself and
therefore
at least the private industry the
private corporations
are beginning to recognize that degrees
are not that important
skills are important so and in the u.s
it's already happening
many companies many many big companies
like google no longer require a college
degree
and that's going to start in india as
well very soon so the value of degrees
is going to
plummet and the value of the iits etc is
also going to plummet very badly
and it's it is something that needs to
happen because these
institutions they don't really perform
any real national service anymore today
so yeah it's going to happen soon it's
already happening
serbojet asks do you think that online
study is going to start a new era of
indian education system
and will it be the right thing or will
it be a blunder it is the right thing
times are changing the world is changing
and we have to keep changing with the
times
the entire world is online now you can
get
any education you want online
for free you will not get a degree for
it but you will get the knowledge and
the skills you can get
any knowledge any skills at any level
online
for free so yes online study is
definitely revolutionizing
education it is not revolutionizing the
education system because the government
is not changing the education system
they still want the same degree based
system to continue but
how long will it last once it becomes
irrelevant
in the in the job market it it will
either
have to change or nobody would be will
basically go for degrees anymore
because once the companies no longer
require a degree and they only look at
the kind of skills you have and it's
easy to assess somebody's skills it's
very easy
to assess a new candidate's skills so
once they start
assessing only your skills and and
ignoring the degrees that is going to be
the end of the
indian education system as it exists
today
so online study is the key to that you
can get all the skills you want
online for free so yes it is starting a
new era
in education in india and it is
hopefully the
beginning of the end of the colonial
commercial
education system that we have today
abhishek asks what role will digital
education play in the coming years
i think the coming years is going to be
only about digital education
everybody today has a cell phone
everybody has some access to the
internet
throughout the country even though india
is still a
a very poor country overall on average
india's per capita gdp is lower than
that of bangladesh today
you know india's population is larger
than that of the entire population of
africa so india has major challenges and
yet
i think almost everybody is now
connected to the internet so yes it is
possible for
every student in india already almost
every student in india
to access digital education so it is
going to
revolutionize the uh
the way people acquire knowledge
and it's up to the government now what
they want to do with it do about this
they can either keep resisting it like
they're resisting bitcoin
and cryptocurrencies or they can
leverage it for the country's good for
the long-term future of the country
so it's for the government to decide are
they still
stuck in the 1970s mindset or do they
have some people who
do understand what the 21st century is
all about
so whether the government does anything
or not digital education is going to
change the world
one mole asks in india exams are given
the utmost
importance and significance compared to
anywhere else in the world
be it in the boards or competitive exams
for some people it's a do or die
situation
how to deal with this exam centric
education system the first thing is that
exams are so
important because we have this
incredible scarcity of education seats
you have so few iits you have so few
good good institutions
and you have hundreds of millions of
students every year
so there is this artificial scarcity the
government needs to create more
institutions
every district should should have an iit
level institution
an iim level institution so that
everybody can get the education they
deserve
they deserve or require or else abolish
all these institutions all together
make everything online and have
so here's the thing why what can we do
about this exam centric system
you know when when you go for a driving
test
is the driving test held once a year
no once you are ready and you are
confident about
your driving skills you can go and book
a driving test any day you like
any day any week any any month of the
year anytime
in the daytime or even the evening i
guess so the driving test
is a test of your skills whether you're
competent in this skill of driving or
not
so why can't we have the same system
for every other skill let's say you want
to
be certified as a as a programmer in a
certain language
or as a as as a scientist let's say
in chemistry or something or whatever
right so any topic
why can't you have these exams why are
the exams held only once a year
why can't these exams be held five times
a week
three 52 weeks of the year and make all
the exams online
make all the exams accessible to
everybody for free
you can take the exam 10 times if you
want and once you and and it should not
in a failure should not count against
you
if you failed a driving test three times
does it count against you
you can do the driving test many times
and when you finally succeed
you're certified as a driver so why
can't the same thing be done
in education let people take an exam
five times and once you
are competent enough and you have
acquired this class then you pass the
exam
at a certain cutoff percentage why can't
we do this
and why can't we have standardization of
exams throughout the country
you have all these different boards in
some places
students get 99 marks and even that's
not enough to get into a college
in some other states even 65 percent is
too much it's very hard to achieve
there is so much disparity so you can't
even compare the level
of the students so we need to have
standardization in the country
and secondly everything needs to be made
online and these
high-stakes exams need to be to be done
away with
every exam entrance exam etc should be
available
let's say you're a student in the 7th
standard
and you have already studied a lot why
why aren't you eligible to try the 10th
standard exam
and if you clear the exam then why can't
you go straight to 11th
why is this option not available so
these are the
some very simple logical things that can
be done
to make it easier for students to
empower the students to go forward
you know so exams
should be should be made this so this
once a year exam thing
is is nonsense it is just another way of
controlling the students and
imposing the system's power over the
students and their parents and the
people of the country
so to empower the people every exam
needs to be made online
and the exam should be available on
demand whenever you feel you're ready
go and take the exam and see how it goes
that's how it should be
that will empower the students
nimitz asks how should the education
system be reformed to promote
creative logical analytical thinking
instead of rote learning
one of the ways can be open book exams
which we had in my university
what are some other changes that can be
done so i just
i just spoke about some things that can
be done i think this open
exam book is a very good open book exam
concept is excellent i know that most
teachers and professors in this country
would be horrified at the concept
that the idea of open book exams because
according to them
learning means memorizing things just
memorizing long paragraphs of text
and then formatting them out in the exam
but if you have an open book exam then
you can just copy paste right
so exams need to be about understanding
about knowledge and not about
memorization rote memorization
so the best way to learn any skill is to
solve lots of problems if you are
learning mathematics
then you learn by solving lots of
problems if you're learning physics
you learn by solving lots of problems
there's no need to memorize things
memorize certain concepts so i
fully agree that there should be open
book exams and
by opening the book you should be able
to access whatever
information you don't need to return in
your brain but the exam should test your
understanding not your memory
that's what it is so yeah that's a great
that's a great idea
it is already done in many western
countries and india unfortunately
relies only on rote memorization which
is a very very
it's something that holds people back
because it doesn't give you any
knowledge it's
exams are just a test of your memory not
of your actual understanding
so these things need to change how
should we reform the system to promote
creative logical analytical thinking
instead of rote learning well
it should the education system should be
uh about
acquiring skills and solving problems if
you do that then
automatically you have to be creative
and logical
and analytical so the entire
process of learning should be about
solving problems
even in history where it's all
apparently about memorizing dates it's
not that
you don't learn history by memorizing
dates i mean people ask me all the time
how do i remember so much about history
the right way to understand history is
to understand causality
what causes what what are the
uh what drives the what are the factors
that drive the world
what is power what is influence
how does geopolitics work what is what
what are the things that cause other
things what is the cause and effect
chain like
when you understand these concepts then
history suddenly suddenly
makes a lot of sense lot more sense
and then you can start understanding
that because a certain thing happened
that's why today we have the situation
today
you can start making connections so
again it's about solving problems
that why did this certain situation
happen at so so and so time in history
so you have to try and understand
logically and think logically why it
happened
that's how you learn so learning has to
be about solving
problems and creating solutions
so once you implement that sort of
system that sort of
program in the education system then you
students will automatically become
creative
and logical and analytical and problem
oriented and solution oriented
that is the way to do it not rote
learning
so good question
krishna saraf asks what can i do in my
own way as a student
to try and reform the education system
making it closer to the gurukul or the
arabic system that worked better for
thousands of years
you see krishna unfortunately there is
absolutely nothing you can do
absolutely nothing you can do as a
student to reform the system
we the citizens have no power
nothing the entirety of the power in
this country
lies with the political class and the
bureaucracy
and various other so-called institutions
there is
absolutely nothing you can do as an
individual
to reform the system there is absolutely
nothing i can do as an individual
to reform the system all i can do is
promote awareness and spread some
knowledge
but it is entirely up to the politicians
whether
they wish to bless us with some changes
or not
it is entirely up to them we the
citizens in this
so-called democracy have zero power we
have no power
we have no influence we can people have
been
begging for changes for decades not just
in the education system
in the in the laws of the country in the
constitution of the country which is
so badly skewed in certain directions
and what are the politicians doing i
mean you must have heard of this free
temple
movement this has been
an issue for decades what is the
government doing
so we the people have no power
unfortunately in the system
that's why we need leaders who are
actually on our side who actually serve
the people in the country
that's what we need that's what this
country needs
to climb out of the colonial bog
that is that it is in that's what we
need
sandeep asks can we remove the
attendance rule so we can learn in other
ways absolutely
attendance the attendance rule that you
need to have a certain 70 percent or 80
percent or 90
attendance it is just another way of
controlling you
it's just another way of showing you
who's the boss who's in power who's in
charge
why do you need attendance today i'm
glad that we have this online learning
this so-called pandemic has
at least done away with the so-called
attendance rule but i think now they are
they are
making it mandatory to attend online and
all that this is nonsense
this power that the education system has
over the students is is
it is it is not doing any good to the
students
all that is required of the education
system is that the student
learns and learning can be done in any
way
you don't have to be present and listen
to that
dull monotonous teacher
droning on saying repeat after me repeat
after me listen to me
and reading out from a book who needs
that you can learn on your own
everybody has is born with a certain
intelligence indians are the most
intelligent people in the world
so this attendance rule is another
colonial leftover
that needs to be done away with i
absolutely agree with you sandeep
pushkar asks the department-related
parliamentary standing committee on
education
under the new education system has asked
for suggestions
from teachers in rewriting the history
textbooks what all suggestions could
have been given
the suggestions have been asked from the
citizens
there is this uh online portal i think
and there's this email address where you
can send an email
suggesting what changes need to be made
in the
in the history textbooks etc
okay so let's take a look at this what's
the population of india
let's it's it's 1.3 billion 1.3
something billion
let's round it up to 1 billion now how
many
what percentage of indians will send a
suggestion to this
uh about this let's say one person
no let's say 0.1 because most people
don't care
but let's say out of the 1 billion
people in india 0.1 percent
people will send an email with some
suggestions
so that is 10 million people is it 10
million people
or is it yeah it's 1 million people yeah
0.1 percent of a billion is 1 million
so let's say 1 million people respond
okay and let us say the email is at
least 100 words long
it's going to be longer than that let's
say just for the sake of argument it's a
hundred words
so the total number of words this
so-called parliamentary standing
committee
will receive they will receive a total
of a hundred
million words of suggestions
now i can assure you that the entirety
of the
of this syllabus is less than 100
million words
it is easier to go through the entire
syllabus
for these experts and find the problems
themselves
instead of reading 100 million words of
emails
you understand this entire
process that they have implemented is
self-defeating it is
much more work to read the emails and
suggestions than to read the textbooks
themselves
and find the solutions on their on your
own as experts why can't the government
simply
appoint a committee of 10 20 50 100
experts
in these subjects who will on their
own find the problems as experts
and implement the right solutions
instead of putting all the owners and
responsibility on the citizens
who will send hundreds of millions of
words which these experts
now have to read this is a stupid
process you cannot
ask the people to give
to to give suggestions and then we will
implement them on the basis of democracy
no
leadership is not about implementing
things by by consensus
it's about appointing experts who are
competent enough
to determine on their own where the
problems lie
and to solve these problems and to
rectify the textbooks
this is my view on it i have sent my
suggestion but come on
this is a really stupid way of doing
things
ajay dubai asks why is teaching hinduism
banned in the education system but
teaching other religions
is not banned while it's very simple
ajay and my friends
it's because india is the world's most
hinduphobic country
india's laws are hindu phobic
there are sections in india's
constitution that are explicitly hindu
phobic
and india's government policies
everything are hindu phobic
the so-called rte act right to education
act is hindu phobic
they've given it a very nice name right
to education
act rte act but if you actually examine
the text of this act
it is blatantly hinduphobic so india is
the world's most endophobic country
whether you realize it or not because
hindus in india
have been for centuries so mentally
conditioned
in accepting these discriminatory
practices that they don't even realize
how hindu phobic the system is
hindus have more rights in the united
states
than in india hindus have more rights in
europe
in india than in india there is more
equality for hindus in the united states
or in europe
than in india and that is the reason why
teaching hinduism is banned
but teaching other religions is very
much welcome
in india's education system
prathiksa asks i believe that the educ
that the reservation system
proves to be an obstacle to the overall
growth of our country
what are my views about this
you see reservation i think the
intent behind the reservation system was
good
it was um to provide
better opportunities to people who are
who are
underprivileged because of uh
historical reasons because of what
happened during the colonial era during
the foreign occupation era of india
but i think that the reservation system
basically it defeats the entire concept
of merit
today the reservation system has been
gamed it has been hacked
and people use it to progress
and climb over other people reservation
system is is a
terrible burden on the country if you
have to have a reservation system
it should be not on the basis of your
so-called caste it should be on the
basis of your financial and economic
status
that's all and the best way to ensure
equality
is to make education completely free for
all it should be state funded state
subsidized
that entirely completely totally solves
the problem
so yes the reservation system is a
terrible burden on the country
it's an obstacle to the growth of the
country a country which is
not a meritocracy is is going to go
nowhere
you need to have a a strict meritocracy
in order to have a to to have a good
future
you know so that's what needs to happen
and the best solution is to completely
do away with
exam fees and entrance fees and tuition
fees
and all that make the entire education
system completely free for everybody
then there's no need for reservations
that's it
and again in the case of these academic
staff there should be no reservations
i mean that that's what's destroying the
quality of education
so yeah i agree with you that the
reservation system is
a terrible obstacle to the overall
growth
and progress and the future of the
country
moni deepa says asks do i think that
homeschooling would be better than
following
our current mainstream education system
i think
homeschooling is the best solution if
the parents are able to do it
because it is definitely a big
responsibility
so parents who are working who have jobs
they won't be able to do homeschooling i
mean after they come back from work
will they have the energy to invest
another couple of hours in homeschooling
the children
so it is definitely something that
people
should take seriously take up seriously
if they have the time to do it
it will definitely ensure that your
children get a better education
than the current mainstream education
system definitely
and i think more and more people are now
adopting homeschooling
it is a very good trend so those people
who have the time and the resources to
do it
those who can afford it they should
definitely go for homeschooling i
completely agree with it
aditya asks do you think the new
education policy will change india's
education system
entirely no it does nothing
it is like putting a band-aid on a
gunshot wound
nothing else it is all cosmetic
changes it doesn't address the real
issues
in any way i don't think the new
education system is any kind of
any change in the right direction no
soviet chaudhary asks the education
system in india is outdated
in technical colleges we are taught
subjects which are not relevant in real
life
why don't they reform the syllabus and
introduce
subjects like artificial intelligence
cyber security big data
and make it more skill based secondly
why
isn't it that sports has made a
mandatory subject in indian schools
as in many countries sports is mandatory
very good questions you need we need to
have a
full well-rounded life children should
not be forced to only study all day and
that's it
children should go out enjoy the
sunlight
enjoy sports be physically fit
physically active
sports should be made mandatory
i'm not saying everybody should be
forced to go to the gym and lift weights
or everybody should be forced to go and
play certain sports no
everybody is different everybody has a
different physique different body
everybody should be allowed to play any
sport that is best for them and best
suited for them
so these things need to be
present in the education system so i
agree sports should be made
if not mandatory it should be definitely
available as an
option for every student so yeah i agree
with that
secondly yeah the education system is
outdated we are not taught
any relevant subjects we are still
taught english
literature whatever on earth that is
we are still taught commerce what is
commerce
why are we why aren't we taught
entrepreneurship
we're not taught entrepreneurship we're
taught commerce we are taught history
and civics i mean we are taught
everything that was taught in the 19th
century and the
20th century our system hasn't caught up
with the 21st century
we need to introduce relevant subjects
and we need to have skill-based
education we need to have vocation-based
education that is what the country needs
and the education system this so-called
new education policy is
basically doing nothing to address
these concerns and these issues
so i agree education should be skill
based education should be vocation based
not everybody wants to be a be an
academician
and that's why people don't need
master's degrees i think after the 12th
standard
you should have these vocational courses
diplomas one year diploma
in in it or two-year diploma in in
full-stack web development or one-year
diploma in graphic design
or cyber security artificial
intelligence big data whatever
we need to have this focused laser
focused
one year and two year degree courses or
diploma courses that will prepare you
for
with actual skills that you will
take from the education system with a
great deal of confidence
that you can go and actually solve
real-world problems that's what needs to
be done
the new education policy does not
address any of these things in
any amount of well at any
significant level unfortunately
joseph asks are kids mature enough to
learn history
we have been under the invasion and
occupation of foreigners for a thousand
years
how can we teach them the reality
without generating
unnecessary hatred towards the current
the generation of invaders
what's the right way to teach history
very good question joseph
firstly i don't think that there is any
current generation of invaders
the people in india the indian citizens
who
follow foreign religions they are not
invaders they are not the descendants of
invaders they are they are they are our
own people
whose and whose ancestors had to go
through
horrible experiences and
what happened happened at that time so
yeah good question are kids mature
enough to learn history i think kids are
mature enough to learn history
we have to face the world we have to
face reality
it can be introduced to kids in a
gradual phased manner but it is
essential it is crucial to learn
our true history
it is you we will we will never
have a future unless we know our past
the past is horrific i know
what happened in the past 1000 years is
the most horrific episode in human
history
and for some reason it is all entirely
whitewashed out of our history textbooks
so it needs to be taught without
generating without see basically
the simple fact is that nobody who lives
in india today
is any is in any way responsible for
what happened
over the past 1000 years it is no one's
fault
the people who did those atrocities
aren't alive today
and the people who are alive today in
india are not responsible for what
people did in the past so as long as
this is communicated clearly to students
to students
then they will be able to learn history
without without generating any kind of
hatred
or ranker or ill will towards anybody
towards any section of india's society
so we have to make it very clear that
all indian citizens are the same
we are all descendants of the same great
civilization
we are all equal we all have equal
rights equal privileges
and whatever happened in the past is not
the fault of anybody
who is alive today but we
have to address the past we have to know
the truth
we need to know the figures and
statistics
and the truth of what really happened
and that's it
and so we have to understand the lessons
of history
unless we understand the lessons of
history unless we learn these lessons
we will keep on making the same mistakes
over and over again
and that is what the current system is
designed to be it is designed
to lead indian citizens down the same
paths of self-destruction
so yes we need to be taught history but
it has to be put across in the right
manner
that's all
okay good question india hasn't produced
a sing a science
nobel laureates who lives and works in
india since
siviraman what do you think needs to
change in our education system and
research institutions
to make that possible again okay so
firstly what needs to be done at the
primary level
kids need to be taught mathematics
properly our teachers are incompetent
today they teach mathematics in a
horrible fashion
which ensures that children never really
are able to learn higher mathematics
because if the very foundations are
faulty then you can never progress
further
so first of all teach maths properly
math is the easiest subject in the world
to learn
despite what you may think it's the
easiest subject in the world to learn
if it is taught the right way first of
all like i said
learn math teach math properly secondly
teach the scientific method
this is what needs to happen in the in
the
primary education system the and in the
higher education system
the entire system needs to be based on
research
so basically what we have today is even
in the
bachelor's degree level or master's
degree level or even phd level
there is no real focus on actual
research
the quality of research is pathetic in
india
i mean look at i mean just take a look
at the average phd thesis
in any science physics
chemistry biology mathematics the
quality of the average indian phd is
abysmal
it is not the fault of the students it's
the fall of the professors
in the education system so this needs to
change
our higher education system at the
master's degree level in the in the phd
level
should be fully focused on actual
genuine research so we need to get rid
of the current crop
of academicians who have who have been
brought up in this environment
where the only factor
that leads to promotions is your ability
to play politics
so these people so the system basically
it promotes mediocrity it destroys the
talent
that is what the education system is
currently about
so then the majority of india's
professors i would say more than 95
are mediocre and they need to be
replaced and i can say this openly
because i am no longer associated with
india's education system with the
academic system
so yeah that's what needs to happen
so if certain changes like these are
made
then we will be able to produce high
quality researchers
young people who do very good world
class
research secondly the nobel prizes they
are highly political
i would recommend uh there's this book
very very famous book the beautiful mind
a beautiful mind
there's a movie made about it it's the
life story of john forbes nash so
in this book there is a very good
exposition
of the dirty politics that is involved
in the selection
of the nobel prize winners it's all
political
the indian the great indian physicist
what's his name george the sudarshan
he should have won a nobel prize three
times
there were three nobel prizes awarded to
other people for work that he did
so that's the kind of bias that you have
in the nobel prizes
so indians should not aspire for nobel
prizes
indian politicians should not aspire for
nobel prizes indian scientists should
not aspire for nobel prizes
what we need is we need to have our own
prizes
why can't we have a brahmagupta prize or
an aryabhatta prize
in in the sciences why can't we have a
madhava prize
or a ramanujan prize in mathematics
and so on and these prices should not be
token prices
you get a medal and 10 000 rupees no no
no no
these should be genuine prices each
price should be i would say 10 crore
rupees
just imagine the kind of research that
will start coming out of india
when you have that sort of price at
stake every year
one person will get 10 crore rupees for
their research
and it should be given awarded only to
real world quality world-class research
so these are some simple things that we
can do in india
to change the entire system and the the
entire paradigm of research
akash asks how can we stop the brain
drain so let's understand the causes of
the brain drain
students in india the brain drain
happens at the
higher levels of education right once
you're at the master's degree level of
the phd level that's when
people leave the country mostly forever
for good
why does it happen let's say you are in
an iit in india
you go to the iit with great
expectations it's one of the greatest
institutes in the country
and what do you find you find mediocre
teachers
who are not interested in any real
research you find that the
that the assembly hall and the
conference room
and the washroom all cost crores of
rupees the equipment that cost
growth of rupees but you find that your
lab has equipment that's 10 20 30 years
old it's obsolete so you can't really do
any real research there
any real technological research you find
that the administrators
who run the iits and other institutions
they invest
all the money that is supposedly to be
invested in science
in the wrong places they invested in
these crow
million dollar washrooms million dollar
auditoriums etc so then you get
demoralized
as a student and you find that these
teachers they don't really care about
the subject they have no passion for the
subject
and then you find that even if you are a
good student
you are not valued and you will find
that the
bureaucracy treats you like garbage you
find that the job market also is very
competitive and there's not
much you can achieve and that's why you
leave the country
and that is the reason for the brain
drain everybody loves the country
people prefer to live in their country
you go to the us
you will find that indians still
congregate together they are happy in
each other's company they still want to
recreate a part of india over there
so they desperately miss the country
they love the country
but the country doesn't value talent the
country doesn't reward talent
and that's why they are forced to leave
the country so once the system changes
once india becomes a meritocracy one
once india does away with this
reservation system once india
rejects mediocrity in the education
system in the professors
in the teachers and the staff etc and
when india starts rewarding talent fully
that's when the brain drain would be
stopped see how china has done it
very simple very good example the
chinese have reversed
brain drain they still have people all
over the world
but they use those people as strategic
assets
so there's a lot of india can learn from
china on how to reverse this brain drain
and
and how to reform the education system
my name franco singh asks i have seen
many of my colleagues not knowing much
about indian history
what they know is just mughals and
independence so called
struggle tell us what went wrong and
what can be done in order to shape the
future of india
because the present generation needs
unity and understanding of their
ancestors to get motivated and more
proud of ourselves yes
so what went wrong what went wrong is
that the british handed over power
to people of their choice they handed
power
after independence to basically
the people who continued the same legacy
and the same system
right we got independence on the terms
that were given to us
by the british we did not get
independence on our own terms
because we did not snatch independence
from them we took it as if it's a great
donation
so that's why the system has continued
and the system was designed
to make indians ashamed of themselves it
was designed
to give indians the wrong information
about their past and about their
ancestry about their ancestors
and so that indians would always keep on
feeling ashamed of themselves and their
ancestors
and the main purpose of the system is to
divide indians
divide north from south east from west
tamil from sanskrit
gujarati from marathi manipuri from
nagaland
and god knows what you know kashmir from
india
now bengal from india the entire purpose
of the education system the academic
system is to divide
the country go and look into any
humanities department
in india and see the kind of so-called
research paper they're producing
it's all about division it's all about
identity politics
go and see what the so-called tata
institute of
social sciences or whatever tiss is
producing the kind of
so the kind of alleged research they
produce
see that to the titles so the topics so
the education system
basically it acts as
a tool of foreign powers who wish to
divide and destroy india right
it doesn't serve as as an as an
institution
that will take the country forward so
what is needed my friend
is the entire overhaul of the academic
system
not some small cosmetic changes here and
there not a little bit of syllabus
change here oh now we have certain
things in our syllabus
come on the entire system
needs to be changed so that's what needs
to happen it's
it's a big ask for sure
and to run to to run a country
as large as india you need a superhuman
leader
if you look at the leaders in the past
2000 years
if you study history of the past two
thousand years
you will see what kind of leaders india
needs think about the great leaders past
two thousand years
kanishka the great the great emperor you
had the
samadhira gupta the great emperor gupta
you had the great um
who else do we have we have so few great
leaders don't we
the great chatrapati shivaji maharaj so
these are people who unified the country
didn't they
and they were really tall leaders great
leaders
super heroes in a way so these people
have certain characteristics
even look at other countries the kind of
great people who have unified countries
after strife
the great ching is khan who came out of
nowhere and unified
a nation that was fragmented for
centuries
if you look at mustafa kemal ataturk who
brought turkey back
from the brink of disaster after the
collapse of the ottoman empire
all of these great people they have
certain characteristics
they are all young men they're all young
men
think about lord rama how old was he
when he did these great deeds
he was in his twenties for the sake of
the gods
he went and fought the great war in
lanka and rescued
his wife back when he was in his
twenties
think about any great leader in this
country when have they done the greatest
deeds in their life
when they were young india needs young
leaders look at india's political
leadership today
the if you look at the past history the
oldest of these great leaders
is ching is khan he started his career
as a great leader as a conqueror when he
was in his mid 40s mid to late 40s
but he was a one in 2000 years kind of
person
so the kind of india the kind of leaders
india needs
is younger people because older people
are set in their ways they have
outdated ideas i'm not saying they're
bad people
or they want something bad for the
country but they don't have the
energy and the passion and the
understanding of technology
in the 21st century the way younger
people have india needs younger
leaders and that has to come from the
education system the education system
should
produce and promote leaders not
political leaders
like these student leaders and all that
azadi
that is nonsense man india needs real
leaders and that needs to come from the
education system
and leadership has to be young i'm not
saying all leaders should be young
we need to have a good mix i'm not i am
not against older people please
it's not that way older people are much
wiser than younger people but younger
people have more
energy and enthusiasm than older people
so india needs a good blend
a good mix of various age groups but
it's
always historically been seen that it is
younger leaders who take the country
forward so these are some of the lessons
of history my friends
so uh thank you very much for all the
questions it's been way over
90 minutes uh so i'm gonna
should i take a few live chat questions
shall i
okay let me take a couple of live chat
questions
sudan show uh one second let me remove
this
okay sudan says lack of self-respect is
why most
indians underestimate their own
historical greatness
and lack leadership qualities how do you
think this self-respect can be restored
simply by knowing your true history
if we are we are not taught over real
estate that's why we don't have the
self-respect
once we learn our true history the
pre-invasion
history of india then we will know
how great this country was and how
immense the achievements of our
ancestors were in all fields in science
in architecture in
in the arts in culture in conquests
beyond india everything in the military
domain
in every sphere all indians need to to
all that needs to happen is that indians
need to be taught their real history
through without the intervening lens of
any
political ideology that's all that's all
that needs to happen
olivier asks we can't change the entire
system how to start
small and how can we as a research
fellow change this well the system is
the system
unless the government changes nothing
will happen how can we as a research
fellow or as individuals change it the
most
we as individuals the most an individual
can do
as a student is to acquire skills
outside of the education system acquire
skills on their own
as an extracurricular activity so it is
not part of your
education curriculum but you will invest
some more time
in yourself in your own future by
acquiring additional skills
in your free time that is the best you
can do as of today
and the best you can do to serve the
country is to fulfill your
your potential understand who you are
understand what is your
what is what you are best at what are
your qualities your best qualities
and invest in those qualities
and become the best version of yourself
in the long run
and that's the best you can do apart
from that it's about
up to the politicians to change the
system
okay let me see some other questions
about education
uh okay this is not about education
okay chirag asked why is it that we have
got so few competent
good leaders almost negligible since
1947 after the independence from the
british
it's because the system is designed to
promote
leaders who are mediocre the political
system
ensures that outsiders are kept out
and only the powerful remain powerful
and then their children come into the
picture and they become powerful
the political system ensures that the
common man or woman
cannot succeed in politics unless they
become part of the system
and make the same compromises you see
it's like this everybody has the right
to vote but
does the system give you the right to
stand for election does it give you a
fair chance to win an election
let's say you want to stand for election
okay in some election let's say
you want to stand for parliament as an
independent
and you go and register for the thing
assuming that they don't throw out
your nomination you stand
as the candidate do you stand any chance
against other candidates from political
parties they have
hundreds of close of rupees to throw in
the election campaign to buy publicity
and whatnot
what do you have as an independent
citizen
you have nothing you don't have that
sort of money which means that you will
never stand a chance of winning an
election
so the system is designed in a way that
it keeps the citizens
out of the power structures
only the powerful who became powerful
because of the british their descendants
are still continuing
in certain political parties you do have
some more meritocracy
our current prime minister has come up
through a great deal of struggle so
there is meritocracy in that political
party
in other parties it's just one family
that rules i'm not talking about
any single political party there are
many such examples so that is the
characteristic
of our political system and that is why
it just keeps on producing the same kind
of
politician that's the thing
okay i will take one more question and
then we'll be done for today
why not start a wiki within real indian
history why not start a wiki
with real indian history community
driven with the real experts well
who decides who's an expert where do we
find these experts
and maintaining a wiki is an extremely
time consuming task
for somebody who has maybe an hour of
spare time
in his or her day how does that person
maintain a wiki
you need a great deal of investment you
need to hire people
and so on and who determines who's an
expert everybody will put their hands up
i'm an expert i'm an expert
but who who curates
the experts you know
i mean everybody's perception of who's
an expert is different
your perception will be different my
perception will be different so
that is the problem what needs to happen
is that the people we have elected
need to drive this change we are paying
them
to make the country better we are paying
them to administer and govern the
country and to
improve the system that's what needs to
happen
we can try this but it is it is a very
very uphill task
this is this is like a full-time job to
start a wiki and you need to write
so much i mean creating a wiki
administering the site is one thing but
coming but creating all the content
is a very time consuming job it takes
six months to one year to write a medium
sized book
a wiki is like thousands of books so you
would not need thousands of people
but then they will not all be experts
right and then you run into the same
quality issues
so that is the challenge that faces us
and that's why it is the government's
job with all
its immense resources and immense money
to do these things and thus far they are
abdicating the duty
so that is so we have discussed some of
the problems many of the problems in the
education system today
i am very thankful to all of you for
asking these wonderful questions
very incisive questions brilliant
questions
i had no idea this topic would be so
important to all of you
but thank you for all the questions and
so i'm gonna end this now but
next week so this is a warm-up session
we have just concluded
next week i am going to do a proper
presentation to all of you
i'm gonna do a proper structured
presentation
of what the education system is like
what is the purpose of education
what is the history of what went wrong
what are the
defects and problems in the current
education system in india
and what are the solutions that i
would implement if i had the chance
so that is what i will talk about next
week so to conclude let me
uh one second
to conclude let me
thank uh siddhan singh and lalit mishira
for their contribution
and for the support of the to this
channel and thank you everybody
thank you stay energetic thank you
everyone for this wonderful session
and i will see you tomorrow thank you
bye